MUSIC
Hello everyone. In today's module we will discuss
about introduction to food microbiology and food safety.
The primary objectives of this module are to
introduce history and progression of
food microbiology and food safety.
To learn the basic concept and scope of
food microbiology and food safety, and to recognize
the role of food microbiologist and current
status of food microbiology and food safety.
So in this module, you will learn an important
historical developments in food microbiology and food safety.
The role of microorganism in food like food
fermentation, food preservation, foodborne
illnesses, food spoilage, food quality control
and emergence of food safety.
And in the last, scope of food microbiology
and food safety.
MUSIC
Almost every food product has certain kinds
of microorganisms.
Each microorganism has its different role
in food and their presence may influence
the quality and texture of the food.
Some of them have desirable roles
like natural fermentation of the food,
while others causes spoilage and diseases.
In ancient time, people used several methods
of food fermentation, spoilage and preservation.
The relationship between microorganism and
food was not established before eighteen hundred.
Schwann, in eighteen thirty seven discussed about the yeast
which appeared during alcoholic fermentation
and eighteen fifty seven to eighteen seventy six, Pasteur stated
that for the chemical conversion that takes place in
food and beverages, microorganisms were responsible.
These discoveries were considered as an important
milestone in the evolution of food microbiology.
Later on many discoveries were made about
the activity and potential role of microorganisms
in preserving, spoiling and poisoning of food,
spread over globally.
MUSIC
Around eight thousand B.C. agriculture and animal husbandry
were adopted by the early civilizations.
Between eight thousand to one thousand B.C. different
traditional methods for preserving foods such as
drying, cooking, baking, smoking, salting, sugaring
with honey, ice, storage in pits, fermentation
with grains, fruits, milk, pickling and spicing
were used mainly to diminish spoilage.
A practice for fermentation was commonly used
by many communities for preserving foods
and to produce different kinds of popular foods
using fruits, vegetables and milk.
Around the sixteen seventies, after ubiquitous acceptance
of existence of bacteria and yeasts by Leeuwenhoek,
some researchers explored the potential role
of such microorganisms with different types
of food in terms of fermentation, spoilage
and illnesses associated with food.
During eighteen seventies, Pasteur initiated the
possible applications and role of microorganisms in
food and also proved their scientific evidence.
Above findings paved the path of
success in the further development of
early food microbiology in the twentieth century.
Few major developments and most significant
dates, events and contributions of scientists
in the history of spoilage, food poisoning,
preservation, microbiological techniques and
food legislations are described till twentieth century.
MUSIC
The important discoveries and developments
in food spoilage.
During sixteen hundred to seventeen hundred,
existence of bacteria in milk was confirmed by Kircher.
Yeast cells were firstly observed by Leeuwenhoek.
During seventeen hundred to eighteen hundred The identification of
lactic acid bacteria as the main acid in sour milk by Scheele.
Eighteen hundred to nineteen hundred Slimy beet juice examined
by Kircher. Souring of milk due to the growth
of organisms which was demonstrated by Pasteur.
Cheese ripening was similar to alcoholic and
organic acids fermentation was confirmed.
First report on microbial deterioration of eggs.
And the pure culture of Lactococcus Lactis
was first isolated by Lister. Later on,
ability of pure cultures of bacteria to grow at
zero degrees, demonstrated by Forster.
Study on Thermophilic bacteria and spoilage of canned
corn due to improper heat processing were discovered.
During nineteen hundred to two thousand The term "Osmophilic"
and "Psychrophiles" were used and the isolation
of Bacillus coagulants from coagulated milk
was performed.
MUSIC
The important discoveries and developments
in food poisoning.
During the year eighteen hundred to nineteen hundred Sausage poisoning
and its fatality was described by Justinus Kerner.
Milk as a transmitter of typhoid fever was
reported by Taylor.
Isolation of Salmonella enteritidis from meat and
Clostridium botulinum was discovered by Van Ermengem.
nineteen hundred to two thousand Clostridium botulinum,
Type A strain was documented.
Food poisoning by Bacillus Cereus reported. Paralytic
shellfish poisoning reported.
Yersinia enterocolitica reported as a causative
agent for Gastroenteritis.
Salmonella enterotoxins were discovered.
Infant botulism were reported. Listeriosis
outbreak in U.S. reported.
Campylobacter jejuni enterotoxin reported.
And the approval of irradiation to control
Trichinella spiralis in pork in the U S. was confirmed.
MUSIC
The important discoveries and
development in the area of food preservation
During seventeen hundred to eighteen hundred
Canning of vinegar by Swedish chemist.
During eighteen hundred to nineteen hundred
Preserving of food by canning process was patented.
U.S. patent for preserving food in tin cans
granted.
A patent for making condensed milk granted
to Newton.
Canning in Australia was introduced by S. Elliott.
Sterilization of food by autoclaving, a patent
granted. Commercial pasteurization of milk
in the U.S. Mechanical refrigeration of fruit
storage started in Chicago.
And first bacteriological study of Canning
by Russell.
During nineteen hundred to two thousand Sodium Benzoate
was permitted as a preservative for certain foods.
Preserving fruits and vegetables under
carbon dioxide, a patent was granted to Franks.
Structured study of spore heat resistance
performed by Bigelow and Esty.
Industrial application of controlled atmosphere
storage of apples in Europe.
Ionizing radiation to preserve hamburger meat
by Proctor.
Introduction of D Value concept first time,
and Sorbic acid approved as a food preservative.
MUSIC
The important discoveries and developments
in microbiological techniques
During the year eighteen hundred to nineteen hundred,
first time use of cotton to close tubes and flask to restrict
microbial contamination in heated culture
broths. Methylene blue as a synthetic dye to
stain bacteria in aqueous suspension. Thermal resistance of
Endospore of Bacillus subtilis revealed by F. Cohn.
Pure culture of Streptococcus Lactis was isolated
by serial dilution from sour milk.
Robert Koch and his team first time introduced
several important methods, like solid media
to purify and enumerate bacteria, Petri dish,
flagellar staining techniques, steam sterilization
of media that works above boiling point of
water and some photography of cells and spores.
Hans Christian Gram developed Gram's stain
for staining of bacterial cells.
MUSIC
Important developments in food legislation. During the year
eighteen hundred to nineteen hundred national meat
inspection law enacted and compulsory for
the inspection of meats for export purpose only.
Amendment in previous meat inspection Act. During nineteen hundred
to two thousand U.S. FDA approved by the Congress.
A requirement of pasteurization of
milk order was issued.
New Food, Drug and Cosmetic Act
enacted as law.
Miller pesticide chemicals Amendment to Food,
Drug and Cosmetic Act was approved by Congress.
Compulsory poultry and poultry product Law
in US was enacted.
Use of irradiation for preservation of bacon
approved by U.S. FDA and developed HACCP regulation
for meat and poultry, fishery product and juice product
first time. Recently, the importance
of microorganisms in the food has increased a lot, due to
their important role in food production.
They can be either beneficial or harmful.
In terms of importance,
all the groups of micro organisms are not
equal interest for a food microbiologist because of
different nature and their metabolites.
MUSIC
The important microbial groups associated with
the food are bacteria, molds, yeast, viruses, protozoa and algae.
MUSIC
Food safety is a matter of great concern for all of us,
as it begins from crop to gut.
An individual may or may not be aware of it,
before having a meal.
But there are many other persons belonging
to various fields like farming, research, industry,
government or non-government offices who had great
concerns about the food being served to them.
Safety of food cannot be achieved by a single
individual; it is a joint responsibility of
everyone who is involved in it.
It can be farmer, food processor, consumer
or food regulatory authority. Food is considered
safe for human being when it is free from all kinds
of hazards which may be responsible for diseases.
MUSIC
In ancient time, people were not aware of
foodborne diseases or food safety.
Although it was known to the people that food spoils.
However, they were not aware of the reason
behind the spoilage of food and subsequent
disease from the consumption of spoiled food.
After the late nineteenth century, scientists have
begun to understand about the bacteria and
their relationship to disease.
That is why, the history of food safety is the
actually the history of various finding, invention,
food regulations and standards that all led to
the knowledge of present time.
MUSIC
The developments of last two decades in the
area of food safety are presented in this slide.
MUSIC
The safety of food is affected by four factors
Changing demographics, lifestyle and demand
of consumer, food production and economics,
and the emergence of new pathogenic microorganisms.
MUSIC
The prime objective of an implementation of
the food safety management system in food
establishments is the is to provide a preventive approach
to identify, prevent and reduce food borne hazards,
like physical, chemical and biological
agents which could minimize the risk of food poisoning
and to make food safe for eating.
A well-designed FSMS with necessary control
measures can help food manufacturing units to
comply with food hygiene regulations and
to ensure that food prepared for sale is
hygienic and safe for consumers.
These programs are preventive in nature and
are implemented by experienced
professional staff at various stages of food production
to minimize the exposure of food to contaminants.
Many food safety and quality management programs
are integrated to produce safe and hygiene
food consistently for human consumption.
These programmes include Good Agricultural
Practices, that is called GAP,
Good Manufacturing practices (GMP), Good Hygienic practices (GHP),
Hazard Analysis and Critical Control Point (HACCP),
Quality Management Systems (QMS), ISO 9001,
Food Safety Management System (FSMS), ISO 22000
and Microbiological Risk Assessment.
MUSIC
The implementation of food safety involves a blend
of laws, standards and accepted good practices, involving
Government it can be central or state government.
International organizations Like WTO and
Codex Alimentarius Commission. Industry organization,
Research agencies, Independent standard bodies,
and Independent certification bodies.
MUSIC
The major focus area of food microbiology
and food safety are food spoilage, food illnesses,
food fermentation, food preservation, food
hygiene and sanitation and food service establishment,
microbiological risk assessment of food and
quality control in food industry.
In food service sector, there are several
designation which could be given to a food
microbiology professional based on their qualification
and professional training such as
Food Safety Supervisor, Quality Control Officer or Quality
Assurance or Management professional in food/ hospitality/
retail industry and food testing laboratory.
Food Safety Officer in the food regulatory
bodies or organizations.
Food Safety Project Microbiologist or Research
Scientist.
Microbiology Supervisor for Food testing.
Food Auditor in certification and inspection
bodies.
Trainer/counselor/consultant/advisor in Food
Safety and Quality Management System, and moreover,
an individual can start his or her
startup as a professional in certifying or
auditing of Food Safety and Quality Management
system.
MUSIC
Food Microbiology and Food safety focuses
on the study of microbial ecology related
to food, like spoilage, fermentation, preservation,
investigation of foodborne outbreaks and
quality control of food in food manufacturing units,
as well as national and international food safety legislations.
The developments which stretched over several
centuries eventually led to the recognition
of importance and more diverse role of microorganisms
in food products.
MUSIC